A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, John E. Craig Files, Accession 2001:069, SG 2 FA1412
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, John E. Craig Files, Accession 2001:069, SG 2
1975-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
Craig, John E.
FA1412
4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series as follows:
Series 1: John E. Craig Chronological Correspondence
Series 2: Congressional File
Series 3: Speeches and Papers
Biographical / Historical
John E. Craig, Jr. served as Vice President and Treasurer of the Commonwealth Fund.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Commonwealth Fund records were donated to RAC in 1985. The initial transfer of archival records to RAC began in 1986, and tranfers continue on a regular basis. These specific John E. Craig files were transferred to RAC in 2001 as accession 2001:069.
Scope and Contents
This set of John E. Craig files, covering the period 1975-1996, consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, speeches, papers, and a small selection of background files pertaining to the Commonwealth Fund's congressional activities and lobbying efforts.
- John E. Craig Chronological Correspondence, 1987-1996; 1; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1988, 1988 January-March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1988, 1988 April-December (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1990, 1990 January-February (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1990, 1990 March-December (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1993 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1994, 1994 January-November (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - John E. Craig Internal Correspondence 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - John E. Craig Internal Correspondence 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Personnel
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1995, 1995 June-December (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - John E. Craig External Correspondence 1996, 1996 January-March (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Congressional File, 1981-1986; 2; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - Congressional Hearings Working File, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - House Membership in the 99th Congress, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Margaret E. Mahoney Testimony, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Congressional Subcommittees, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Foundation Tax Law - History, Problems and Prospects, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Justice for All by James A. Joseph, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Meetings, Washington, D.C., 1983 November 10 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - S. 1857, 1983 November 10-11 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - HR. 4172, 1983 November 10-11 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Testimony - Brian O'Connell - President, Independent Sector, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Foundation Legislation, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Voluntary Agency Lobbying Activities, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Circular A-122, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Reference - Lobbying, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Congressional Representatives, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Representative Rangel, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Independent Sector Memos, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - John Edie (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Charitable Contributions Law (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Hearings Correspondence File, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Municipal Property Tax Hearings Working File, 1983 June 16-17 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Legislative Reference, 1983-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Permanent Charitable Contributions Legislation (H.R. 1315), 1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - New Federal Legislation (Tax Reform Act), 1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Council on Foundations - Legislation (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Speeches and Papers, 1975-1984; 3; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - Cost Effectiveness of Home Health Services, 1975 January (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - NEJM - The Changing Role of Provate Philanthropy in Health Affairs, 1975 May (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - A National Foundation Program of Student Assistance to Minorities, Women and Rural Students in Medicine, Osteopathy and Dentistry, 1976-1980, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Guaranteed Student Loan Program, Fiscal Year 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The Disabled Aged: Craig Report - What Can Private Philanthropy Do, 1977 October (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Health Professional School Finance: Lean Years Ahead, 1977 October (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Black Hospitals: Their Prospects for Survival, 1978 January (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Urban Fiscal Crisis in the United States, National Health Insurance and Municipal Hospitals, 1978 November (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Hartford Paper - Financing Health Care - The Individual, C. Schramm, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Hartford Paper - Possible Projects for Outside Study, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Hartford Paper - Health Policy Studies at the AEI for Public Policy Research, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Hartford Paper - Working Drafts, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Hartford Paper - Higgins, Robert, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Hartford Paper - The Hospital Sector, C. Schramm, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Hartford Paper - Improving the Financing and Organization of Health Care, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Hartford Paper - Improving the Financing and Organization of Providers - The Inpatient Hospital Sector, C. Schramm - Final, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Hartford Paper - Improving the Financing and Organization of Providers - Ambulatory Care, Bice, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Hartford Paper - Influencing Consumers: Health Insurance Benefits, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Hartford Paper - Long-Term Care Revision, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Hartford Paper - Improving the Financing and Organization of Health Care - Leading the Private Sector Toward Solutions - Background Paper, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Hartford Paper - Health Policy Studies at the AEI for Public Policy Research, 1978 March (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - The 1979 Federal Health Budget: A National Health Program, 1978 April (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Health Professional Student Assistance: Evaluation of A Private Foundation Program, 1978 September (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Private Foundation Contribution to International Health, 1979 January (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Primary-Care Manpower Debate: More Light on the Issues, 1979 January (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Improving the Organization and Financing of Health Care: A Role for Large Private Foundations, 1979 February-March (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - John Craig Speech to AAMC - Private Foundations and Academic Medical Centers: An Evolving Partnership, 1979 May (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Private Foundation Health Expenditures: A Survey Analysis, 1979 October (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - John A. Hartford Foundation Chronological File, 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Davidson Seminar on Health Care Economics, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Grantmakers in Health Meeting, 1984 December 11-12 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)